Finding aid to the Marine Leland Papers CA.MS.00077
Smith College Archives
Marine Leland Papers
1805-1984
Smith College Archives
Leland, Marine
CA.MS.00077
5.083 linear feet (13 containers)
Biographical materials, correspondence, manuscripts, photographs, publications, and speeches by Marine Leland, Professor of French and primary contributor to the French Canadian Collection in the William Allen Neilson Library at Smith College.
Biographical / Historical
Marine Leland was born on December 2, 1899 in Québec City to American parents of English descent. She was educated in Montréal at the Sacred Heart Convent and later in Germany, France, Spain, and the United States. From Radcliffe College she received an A.B. (1923), A.M. (1925), and PhD (1928). A member of the French Department at Smith College from 1924 until her retirement in June 1965, she pioneered a new course in French Canadian civilization and is responsible for the forming and building of the French Canadian Collection in the William Allan Neilson Library at Smith. Her contributions to a better understanding of the French Canadian culture has been widely recognized and honored. On May 13, 1983, she died at her home in Northampton, Massachusetts.
Scope and Contents
Biographical materials, correspondence, manuscripts, photographs, publications, and speeches of Marine Leland.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into five (5) series:
Biographical
Correspondence
Professional Life
Oversized Materials
Photographs of French Candians
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Marine Leland Papers were donated to the Smith College Archives from a number of sources. The materials in the collection are formed in part from the faculty file (RG 42) developed during Ms. Leland's lifetime and in part through the efforts of Margaret Storrs Grierson, Archivist Emerita of Smith College. Ms. Grierson donated these materials to the College Archives in August 1983.
French-Canadian literature -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- Massachusetts -- Northampton.; Leland, Marine.; Smith College -- Faculty.; Smith College. Library.
- Biographical
  - Biographical material (Box 909, Folder 1)
  - Biographical - general (Box 909, Folder 2)
  - Notes for autobiography (Box 909, Folder 3)
  - Passports, etc, Identification (Box 909, Folder 4)
  - Photographs (Box 909, Folder 5)
  - Biographical - photographs (Box 909, Folder 6)
  - Samples of School work, 1908-1911 (Box 909, Folder 7)
  - L'Institution des Sourdes - Muettes, 1903-1913 (Box 909, Folder 8)
  - Sacre-Coeur school in Montreal, 1908-1913; 1914-1915 (Box 909, Folder 9)
  - Year in Dresden, 1913-1914 (Box 909, Folder 10)
  - Montfort, 1914-1915 (Box 910, Folder 11)
  - Montreal years, vacations, 1906 (Box 910, Folder 12)
  - Beauvais, 1921-1922 (Box 910, Folder 13)
  - Madrid, 1923-1932 (Box 910, Folder 14a)
  - Madrid, 1923 - 1932 (Box 910, Folder 14b)
  - Noting Marine Leland's death, 1983 (Box 910, Folder 15)
  - Memorial, 1983 (Box 910, Folder 16)
  - Awards and medals (Box 910, Folder 17)
  - Honors and tributes (Box 910, Folder 18)
  - Honorary degree Univ. of Laval, 1952 (Box 910, Folder 19)
  - Honorary degree Univ. of Montreal, 1962 (Box 910, Folder 20)
  - Honorary degree Univ. of Vermont, 1967 (Box 910, Folder 21)
- Correspondence
  - Aluminum Company of Canada (Box 911, Folder 22)
  - Associations (Box 911, Folder 23)
  - American Council of Learned Societies (Box 911, Folder 24)
  - Association for Canadian & Quebec Literatures (Box 911, Folder 25)
  - Association for Canadian Studies in the U.S. (Box 911, Folder 26)
  - Barbeau, Marine (Box 911, Folder 27)
  - Beard, Mary (Box 911, Folder 28)
  - Beaulieu - Burghley (Box 911, Folder 29)
  - Bourassa, Anne (Box 911, Folder 30)
  - Bourassa, Henri (Box 911, Folder 31)
  - Bureau Marguerite - Bourgeoys (Box 911, Folder 32)
  - Cambridge Historical Society/Evangeline Centennial (Box 911, Folder 33)
  - Canadian Bar Association (Box 911, Folder 34)
  - Canadian Broadcasting Corporation I, 1951-1955 (Box 911, Folder 35)
  - Canadian Broadcasting Corporation II (Box 911, Folder 36)
  - Canadian Embassy/Washington (Box 911, Folder 37)
  - Canadian Historical Association (Box 911, Folder 38)
  - Canadian humanities Research Council (Box 911, Folder 39)
  - Canadian Senate (Box 911, Folder 40)
  - Canadian Tour, 1945 (Box 911, Folder 41)
  - Association Canado - Americaine, Corr. I (Box 911, Folder 42)
  - Association Canado - Americaine, 1949-1955 (Box 911, Folder 43)
  - Carleton College, 1947-1948 (Box 911, Folder 44)
  - Carnegie Corporation of New York (Box 911, Folder 45)
  - Canadian Consulate/Boston (Box 911, Folder 46)
  - Clark, Annetta I, Admirers of Society (Box 911, Folder 47)
  - Comite permanent de la Survivance francaise en Amerique (Box 911, Folder 48)
  - C, Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 911, Folder 49)
  - Donner Foundation (Box 911, Folder 50)
  - D (Box 911, Folder 51)
  - F, Miscellaneous (Box 912, Folder 52)
  - Fitzpatrick, Marjorie (Box 912, Folder 53)
  - G, Miscellaneous (Box 912, Folder 54)
  - Garrison, Eleanor & Frank (Box 912, Folder 55)
  - Lionel Groulx, corr. & Foundation (Box 912, Folder 56)
  - Guevremont, Germaine (Box 912, Folder 57)
  - Guggenheim Foundation (Box 912, Folder 58)
  - H, Miscellaneous (Box 912, Folder 59)
  - Ham, Edward (Box 912, Folder 60)
  - Humor/Outrage (Box 912, Folder 61)
  - Huntington, Chapin & Frances (Box 912, Folder 62)
  - Inglis (Box 912, Folder 63)
  - J, Miscellaneous (Box 912, Folder 64)
  - Johnson, Lyndon B. (Box 912, Folder 65)
  - K, Miscellaneous (Box 912, Folder 66)
  - Lambert, Adelard (Box 912, Folder 67)
  - Lanclot, Gustav (Box 912, Folder 68)
  - La Pointe, Renaude (Box 912, Folder 69)
  - Lebel, Maurice (Box 912, Folder 70)
  - Lefevbre, Jean - Jacques (Box 912, Folder 71)
  - Levesque, Sr. M. Antoinette (Box 912, Folder 72)
  - Lortie, Giselle (Box 912, Folder 73)
  - Lorite, Leon (Box 912, Folder 74)
  - Lotbiniere (Box 912, Folder 75)
  - Low, Solon (Box 912, Folder 76)
  - Lower, A.R.M. (Box 912, Folder 77)
  - M, Miscellaneous (Box 912, Folder 78)
  - Modern Language Association (1) Announcements, etc. (Box 912, Folder 79)
  - Modern Language Association (2) Correspondence, Divers hands, 1941 (Box 912, Folder 80)
  - Modern Language Association (3) Correspondence, Divers hands, 1942-1943 (Box 912, Folder 81)
  - Modern Language Association(4) Correspondence, Divers hands, 1944-1945 (Box 912, Folder 82)
  - Modern Language Association (5) Correspondence, Divers hands, 1947-1952 (Box 912, Folder 83)
  - McPherson, Harriet, S.C. Librarian, 1940 (Box 912, Folder 84)
  - Monastre des Augustines, Dieppe, France (Box 912, Folder 85)
  - Monastre des Ursulines, Quebec (Box 912, Folder 86)
  - Montreal, city of (Box 912, Folder 87)
  - Morin, Victor (Box 912, Folder 88)
  - Nolet, Charles & Claire (Box 913, Folder 89)
  - Nolte, Richard (Box 913, Folder 99)
  - Northeast Conference on the teaching of French (Box 913, Folder 91)
  - O (Box 913, Folder 92)
  - P (Box 913, Folder 93)
  - Parkin, Louise (Box 913, Folder 94)
  - Quebec, Province of (Box 913, Folder 95)
  - R (Box 913, Folder 96)
  - Rockefeller Foundation, letters/conference, 1942 (Box 913, Folder 97)
  - S, Miscellaneous (Box 913, Folder 98)
  - Sherbrooke, P.Q. (Box 913, Folder 99)
  - La societe historique de Saguenay (Box 913, Folder 100)
  - Societe Historique franco-americaine (Box 913, Folder 101)
  - Surveyor, Fabre (Box 913, Folder 102)
  - T, Miscellaneous (Box 913, Folder 103)
  - Union Saint jean-Baptisite d'Amerique (Box 913, Folder 104)
  - Universities and Colleges I - Colleges (Box 913, Folder 105)
  - Universite Laval (Box 913, Folder 106)
  - Universities, Miscellaneous, I (Box 913, Folder 107)
  - Universities, Miscellaneous II (Box 913, Folder 108)
  - University of Toronto, Women's War Service Committee (Box 913, Folder 109)
  - V, Miscellaneous (Box 913, Folder 110)
  - W (Box 913, Folder 111)
  - Y (Box 913, Folder 112)
  - Unidentified corr. (Box 913, Folder 113)
- Professional Life
  - Courses (Box 913, Folder 114)
  - McGill University (Box 913, Folder 115)
  - Graduate seminar on French Canada, McGill University, 1967-1968 (Box 913, Folder 116)
  - University of Michigan (Box 913, Folder 117)
  - Shady Hill School, Cambridge, 1923-1924 (Box 913, Folder 118)
  - Smith College, Miscellany of the Years (Box 913, Folder 119)
  - Smith College, 1924-1926; 1928-1965; 1965-1983 (Box 913, Folder 120)
  - Western Reserve, Summer School - Photographs & Clippings (Box 913, Folder 121)
  - Correspondence re. Archives (Bibliography), 1942-1965 (Box 914, Folder 122)
  - Bibliographical correspondence, 1971-1974 (Box 914, Folder 123)
  - Bibliographical correspondence, 1975-1978 (Box 914, Folder 124)
  - Smith College Library (Neilson) Building the French Canadian Collection, I (Box 914, Folder 125)
  - Building the French Canadian Collection II (Box 914, Folder 126)
  - Building the French Canadian Collection III (Box 914, Folder 127)
  - Building the French Canadian Collection IV (Box 914, Folder 128)
  - Building the French Canadian Collection V (Box 914, Folder 129)
  - Leon Lorie text, seminar, 1962 (Box 914, Folder 130)
  - Institute of Current World Affairs (Box 914, Folder 131)
  - Lecture, Bound Volume: Newsletters, M. Leland, Institue of Current World Affairs, 1973 (Box 914, Folder 132)
  - Francois Joseph Cugnet, Bibliotheque, working papers I (Box 915, Folder 133)
  - Cugnet, working papers II (Box 915, Folder 134)
  - Cugnet, working papers III (Box 915, Folder 135)
  - Jacques Cartier & The Saint Lawrence River (Box 915, Folder 136)
  - Famille Guy, working papers (Box 915, Folder 137)
  - Princeton Guy, working papers (Box 915, Folder 138)
  - Madame Lebeau and Captain Baker (Box 915, Folder 139)
  - Marine Leland Bibliography (Box 915, Folder 140)
  - Working Papers on Lotbiniere, Perraults, Guy Cugnet.. (Box 915, Folder 141)
  - Cornet Parsons, Mary Bliss Parsons (Box 915, Folder 142)
  - Junior Bazaar Article (Box 915, Folder 143)
  - Amis d'enfance, publication; F.F.F.A., ms. (Box 915, Folder 144)
  - Dos Culturas canadienses, Introduction Buenos Aires, ms (Box 915, Folder 145)
  - Book Review (French Review), ms.; Klinck, G.A., 1945 (Box 915, Folder 146)
  - Adrienne Monier, rough draft ms. (Box 915, Folder 147)
  - Book Review (Political Science Quarterly), ms. - Wade, M., author, 1956 (Box 915, Folder 148)
  - Raymond Vezina on Bourassa & Leland with M.L. revision, 1977 (Box 915, Folder 149)
  - French Canada: Example of What America is Learning & Modern Language Journal, Dec., 1945 (Box 916, Folder 150)
  - Les Linguistes Etatsuniens et la Tradition Francaise en Amerique, Relations, 1942 (Box 916, Folder 151)
  - Modern French Canada (Box 916, Folder 152)
  - La Modern Language Association et le Canada Francaise, Relations, 1942 (Box 916, Folder 153)
  - Modern Language Journal, May, 1942 (Box 916, Folder 154)
  - Northeast Conference Report: Quebec, French Canada (Box 916, Folder 155)
  - Joseph Francois Perrault (Box 916, Folder 156)
  - Quelques Observations... de Henri Bourassa, Canadian Historical Association, Report, 1951 (Box 916, Folder 157)
  - Madame de Repentigny (Box 916, Folder 158)
  - Review by M.L., Romanic Review, 1956 (Box 916, Folder 159)
  - The Smith College Group, 1930 (Box 916, Folder 160)
  - Canadians Invent Words, Sophian, 1954 (Box 916, Folder 161)
  - Le Travailleur, ms. (Box 916, Folder 162)
  - La Vie Intellectuelle au Canada Francais, French Review, 1948 (Box 916, Folder 163)
  - Publications, Correspondence, 1941-1981 (Box 916, Folder 164)
  - American Undergraduates Abroad, Radcliffe Quarterly, 1930 (Box 9, Folder 165)
  - Approach to Proust (Box 9, Folder 166)
  - A Canadian Explorer in Deerfield, Connecticut Valley Historical Museum (Box 9, Folder 167)
  - Bourassa vu par une Americaine (Box 9, Folder 168)
  - Contribution of Modern Languages in the Present Conflict, National Association of Principals of Schools for Girls, 1942 (Box 9, Folder 169)
  - Francois-Joseph Cugnet XXII. La Revue de l'Universite Laval, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 170)
  - Francois-Joseph Cugnet, La Revue de L'Universite Laval, 1961-1966 (Box 9, Folder 171)
  - Jean-Baptiste Cugnet, traitre? Revue de l'Universite d'Ottawa, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 172)
  - Histoire d'une tradition "Jean-Baptiste Cugnet, traitre a son roi et a son pays," Revie de l'Universite d'Ottawa, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 173)
  - Fort Ticonderoga, 1955 (Box 9, Folder 174)
  - "Canadiana.. .," Quebec: Poesie Vivante, speech, Smith College (Box 918, Folder 175)
  - Carleton College, 1947 (Box 918, Folder 176)
  - Centennial of Evangeline, speeches, photos, Cambridge Historical Society, 1947 (Box 918, Folder 177)
  - John Stoddard, lecture, Northampton Historical Society, 1954 (Box 918, Folder 178)
  - New England captives who were taken to Canada, Deefield Massacre, speeches (Box 918, Folder 179)
  - Broadcasts, CBC, series of 8, Changing Patterns, I (Box 918, Folder 180)
  - Broadcasts, CBC, II (Box 918, Folder 181)
  - Broadcasts, CBC --- Mrs. Johnson's Narrative of her Captivity, III (Box 918, Folder 182)
  - "Quebec Literature in its American Context" (Box 918, Folder 183)
  - Speeches and miscellaneous (Box 918, Folder 184)
  - Marine Leland (Grierson notes) (Box 918, Folder 185)
  - French Canadian Art, museum exhibit (Box 918, Folder 186)
  - Inscribed to M.L. by Louis - Philippe Cormier, journal article (Box 918, Folder 187)
  - Fabre Surveyer on Jean - Antoine Panet (Box 918, Folder 188)
  - Women, miscellaneous (Box 918, Folder 189)
- Oversized Materials
  - diploma, A.B. from Radcliffe College, 1923 (Box 919, Folder NA)
  - diploma, A.M. from Radcliffe College, 1925 (Box 919, Folder NA)
  - diploma, PhD from Radcliffe College, 1928 (Box 919, Folder NA)
  - Honorary degree, L.H.D from Universite Laval, 1952 (Box 919, Folder NA)
  - Honorary degree. L.H.D. from Universite de Montreal, 1962 (Box 919, Folder NA)
- Photographs of French Canadians
  - Bourgualt Family (Box 920, Folder 190)
  - Canada landscapes/streetscapes (Box 920, Folder 191)
  - Champagne, Nazaire (Box 920, Folder 192)
  - D'aigvillon, La Duchesse (Box 920, Folder 193)
  - International Convention at Quebec, 1864 (Box 920, Folder 194)
  - Laurier, Sir William (Box 920, Folder 195)
  - Montmorency - Kent House (Box 920, Folder 196)
  - Montmorency (Box 920, Folder 197)
  - Misc. (Box 920, Folder 198)
  - Giroux, R.P. (Box 920, Folder 199)
  - Hocquart, Gilles (Box 920, Folder 200)
  - Panet, Jean-Antoine (Box 920, Folder 201)
  - Papineau, Joseph (Box 920, Folder 202)
  - Perrault, Joseph Francois (Box 920, Folder 203)
  - Tessier Family (Box 920, Folder 204)
  - Quebec, 1805; 1810; 1865 (Box 920, Folder 205)
  - Vaudreuil (Box 920, Folder 206)
  - Honorary degree stoles, 1952; 1962 (Box 921)